<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the life &amp; death of Oliver Cromwell the late usurper and pretended protector of England &amp;c. / truely collected and published for a warning to all tyrants and usurpers by J.H.</title>
            <author>Heath, James, 1629-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1335A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28052</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10334330</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10334330</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44909)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1385:17 or 1689:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the life &amp; death of Oliver Cromwell the late usurper and pretended protector of England &amp;c. / truely collected and published for a warning to all tyrants and usurpers by J.H.</title>
                  <author>Heath, James, 1629-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Coles ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging: pages 4 and 5 misnumbered 2 and 4.</note>
                  <note>This item can be found at reels 1385:17 and 1689:17.</note>
                  <note>Wing number H72 cancelled in Wing (CD-ROM, 1996).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44909:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44909:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE <hi>LIFE &amp; DEATH</hi> OF OLIVER CROMWELL</p>
            <p>The late Uſurper, and pretended Protector of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Truely Collected and Publiſhed for a warning to all Tyrants and Uſurpers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. H.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>a knight on horseback</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>F. Coles</hi> at the Lamb in the Old-Baily, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:44909:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44909:2"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY Of the <hi>LIFE</hi> and <hi>DEATH</hi> OF OLIVER CROMWELL The late Uſurper.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Shewing the birth and Parentage, and place of Nativity of the ſaid</hi> Oliver Cromwell.</head>
               <p>THE unparalleld actions of this man, hath made people more curious then otherwiſe, they would be, to know his Riſe and Birth, which otherwiſe might better to the advantag of his memory been yet obſcured and concealed; for it will neither add praiſe nor commendation either to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey or Relations, both which have publiquely proteſted their ſhame and their abhortance of him. So that without prejudice to his Family, who have cleared themſelves of any participation of his Facts, and did and doe deteſt both him and them; you may underſtand; he was the Sonne of <hi>Henry Cromwell,</hi> alias <hi>Williams</hi> the Younger Sonne of Sir <hi>Henry Cromwell</hi> of <hi>Hinohingbrook,</hi> in the County of <hi>Huntingdon</hi> Knight, who ſo magnificently treated,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44909:3"/>
                  <hi>King James</hi> in that place at his coming into <hi>England;</hi> who ſo Loyally and Affectionately loved <hi>King Charles</hi> the Martyr; and who laſtly ſo hated and abominated this ſame <hi>Oliver</hi> his Nephew, God-ſonne and Name-ſake.</p>
               <p>He was Born at <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> in the year 1599. where his Father being a Cadet or younger Brother, as we have ſaid, having no large Eſtate, had intermarried with a <hi>Brewers</hi> Widdow, by whom he had ſome addition of Fortune, and from her ſprung that ſtory of <hi>Olivers</hi> being a Brewer in <hi>Huntingdon:</hi> he was from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy a luſty active Child, and of a ſturdy rough temper, which to remedy in his young years, his Father prudently took this Courſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>How</hi> Oliver <hi>was Educated and brought up in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Cambridge, <hi>and afterwards in</hi> Lincolns Inne, <hi>in the ſtudy of the Law.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ABout the Age therefore of Thirteen or Fourteen years, his Father ſent him to the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to have him tempered and managed by the ſevere Tuition and Diſcipline of the Univerſity; but his Tutor quickly perceived the boyſterous and untractable ſpirit of his Pupill, who was more for action then ſpeculation, and loved Cudgells, Foot-ball-playing, or any Game and Exerciſe better then his Book, ſo that there was no hopes of making him a Shollar, or a learned Man, and much ado there was to keep him ſo in compaſſe, that he became not an open and publique diſhonour to his Friends; (here he was made an actor in the play of the Five Senſes, where he ominouſly ſtumbled at a Crown, which he had alſo dreamed he ſhould once Wear) whereupon he was preſently removed, his Tutor weary and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of diſgrace by him, to <hi>Lincolns-Inne;</hi> where he might with leſſe imputation and obſervance, if his bent were ſo given, royſter it out, and yet without much trouble attaine ſome knowledge in the Lawes to qualifie him for a Countrey Gentleman, and that little Competency his Father could leave him. But no ſuch <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments</hi> would ſink into him, he was for Rougher Arguments and Pleas, Club-law, and indeed what occaſion had he to know and be verſed in the Law, whoſe deſigns and wicked practiſes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards were directly oppoſite to all Lawes both Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44909:3"/>ſo that he continued not long there, but was called home, his Father dying ſoon after and leaving him to his ſwinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of his Manner of Life and Converſation in the Countrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLiver</hi> being come down in the Countrey, and growing ſturdy and of Mans ſtature, frequented all manner of wild Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; who but he at any Match or Game whatſoever, where he would drink and roar with the rudeſt of his Companions, and when his Money which he had ſparingly from his Mother, who yet kept the purſe, failed him; he would make the <hi>Victuallers</hi> truſt him, to ſuch a ruine of his Credit and Reputation, he being as famous for his Raunting and his Scores, as after for his Prayers and Victories, that the Ale-wives of <hi>Huntingdon</hi> if they ſee him coming would ſet up a cry, here comes young <hi>Cromwel,</hi> ſhut up the Doors, and ſo keep him out. But he had better ſucceſſe in the War, for then there was no ſhutting of him out, no Garriſon or Caſtle or ſtrength whatſoever was ſufficient to debar him. But that may be imputable to the luck of his former Atchievments, Fortune being tyed at his Girdle, &amp; keeping a conſtant Tenour with him, for at this Age he would make nothing of beating of Tinkers and ſuch Maſty Fellowes at Quarter ſtaffe, or any ſuch weapon they would chuſe; ſo that he was dreaded by all the Ale-drinkers as well as Ale-wives of the Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>How</hi> Oliver <hi>was reclaymed from theſe loud Courſes, &amp; how he joyned himſelf to the preciſer ſort, and became an Hypocritical Convert.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY theſe debaucht Courſes of Life, and regardleſſe thoughts how the world went, as long as Drink and Company could be had, no matter how nor where; he had ſo endangered his ſmall Eſtate and Patrimony, and was ſo far in debt that nothing robory, he was forced to retire himſelf, and get out of the way, and live privately for private arreſts and judgements which were brought againſt him. In this ſolitary Condition he had time to bethink himſelf of his Condition, and having nothing elſe to do, having play'd a part at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to perſonate another at home,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44909:4"/>ſeeming very penſive and melancholy, and much reſerved in his talk and diſcourſe, which from vaine and frivolous and wild ſpeeches was now altered into ſerious and modeſt and grave language, and ſober expreſſion, which accomodated and ſet forth with a more ſtayed and ſolemne aſpect and geſture, made him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be another kind of perſon, having run from the one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme to the other; from Stark nought to too Good, and twill be a queſtion whether, by the firſt he were more deſtructive to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or by the latter more pernicious to his Countrey.</p>
               <p>This humour ſowred him at laſt into a preciſe Puritaniſme, with whom his zealous deſign was to ingratiate himſelf, who increaſing every day, and being grown to a head-ſtrong Faction, he doubted not but if time ſhould ſerve, which his daring ſpirit (if he had not a familiar,) told him was a coming, to be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal perſon among them, and howſoever to make up his decaies on his Fortunes, by the kind-hearted ſupplies and loanes of the brother-hood, who were very proud of ſuch a proſelyte.</p>
               <p>In a ſhort time after, he had learned to pray, and attained a very ready faculty therein, which he made no nicety to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt upon all occaſions, both in their publique and private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo that he was looked upon by thoſe of his Godly party as their chiefeſt Ornament, and by the reſt of the world as a ſtrange wonder. This Artificial devotion did not onely then advantage him, but ſerved him thereafter through the whole courſe of his Life, and was the main ingredient of all his policies and ſucceſſes. A Friar was an Aſſe to him for ſaying of Prayers, he was able to give him two for one with his Beads and by Rote, and out-ſtript him <hi>Extempore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>How</hi> Oliver, <hi>being noted for his pretended Sanctity, was choſen a</hi> Burgeſſe <hi>of</hi> Cambridge <hi>for the</hi> Long-Parliament. <hi>and the War breaking out, was made a</hi> Captaine <hi>of Horſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY this ſanctimonious vizor and manifeſted zeale for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, which was then in every Mans mouth, he was lookt upon as the fitteſt Inſtrument to promote it in the Parliament, which the King had called in 1640. to redreſſe the grievances of the State and Church and to ſupply his neceſſities; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44909:4"/>the Puritan faction and his Relations by marriage, as Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and alſo <hi>Hambden</hi> of <hi>Buckingham</hi> laboured in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Burgeſſes for the town of <hi>Cambridg</hi> to have him choſen. The Town was generally infected with the ſame Diſeaſe, and therefore it was no hard matter to effect it. Sitting in Parliament as a Member, he quickly ſaw which way the ſtreame went, and therefore reſolved to run one of the firſt with it, &amp; therefore helpt out the Noyſe and Cry for Priviledge, proving a great ſtickler againſt the Prerogative; and to that end endeavouring to widen the breach way made by the Malapertneſſe of Tumults againſt the Kings Perſon and Court, inſomuch that he became conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous and noted for his averſion to the Government. The Flame of thoſe inward burnings now breaking out, and becauſe of his influence on his Country, and his bold confident ſpirit, he was courted with a Commiſſion (which he accepted) under the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> the Parliaments Generall, and was made a Captaine of a Troop of Horſe,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the Exploits</hi> Cromwell <hi>did in the beginning of the</hi> War.</head>
               <p>HAving raiſed his Troop, he marched not preſently with the groſſe and main body of the Army, but was ordered to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue about his own countrey, that ſo his own enterprizes might be the better obſerved, and he taken notice of; ſo that he was a riſing man from the very firſt beginning of our civil confuſions. The firſt ſervice that he appeared in, was the ſeizure of Sir <hi>Henry Conisby,</hi> the Sheriffe of <hi>Hartfordſhire:</hi> when in a gallant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Parliament, he was proclaiming the Commiſſion of Array at St. <hi>Albaus,</hi> and ſending him and other Gentlemen his aſiſtance to <hi>London;</hi> which ſudden and meritorious exploit of his was well reſented, and highly commended by the Parliament. His next piece of diligence was the like ſeizure of Sir <hi>John Pettus</hi> and Forty Gentlemen more, of the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> who were forming a party for the King, and ſecuring them; by which means he broke the neck of any future deſigne in that or the next County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> for the Royal Intereſt; ſo that he had brought all the Eaſtern part of <hi>England</hi> to the Parliaments ſubjection by a bloodleſſe and eaſie Conqueſt: but his other Victories, which were principally aſcribed to him, though they were joyned with him, were very ſanguinous and fatally cruel.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44909:5"/>
               <p> As his laſt home employment, he was ordered to purge and to inſpect the Univerſity, wherein he proceeded with ſo much rigour againſt that place of his own Nurture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it was conceived he would at laſt as mercileſsly uſe his Mother, then bleeding <hi>England</hi> which work being over, and unhappily effected, <hi>Cromwell</hi> was the only man; his prudence, Fortune and Valour every where applauded and extolled, and he reputed for one of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and able Commanders in the Parliaments Army.</p>
               <p>'Twas time therefore now to ſhew him abroad, having Armed, Diſciplined and paid his Men ſo carefully, that there was no doubt of their prevailing upon any equal Enemy, and under the Conduct of ſo Vigilant and Wary a Leader, whoſe only aime it was to keep up his Reputation to greater undertakings. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in order to a Conjunction and aſſiſtance of the <hi>Scots,</hi> who were entred <hi>England,</hi> he was made Lieutenant General to the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> who had raiſed his Army out of the aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Counties, as <hi>Cambridge, Huntingdon, Bedford, Suffold,</hi> &amp;c. Thoſe Armies being joyned, and maſtering the Field (the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>New-caſtle</hi> who oppoſed them, retreating into <hi>York</hi>) they reſolved to beſiege that City: to Reliefe whereof Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> came, and forcing them to draw off from their League, gave them the battel on <hi>Marſton Moor, July</hi> the Second, 1644. In the beginning of the Fight Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> had utterly diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited the right wing of the Army, where Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> and the <hi>Scots</hi> Horſe ſtood and diſordered the main body of the Foot, ſo that the day was given for loſt, the <hi>Scots</hi> running and throwing down their Arms; when <hi>Cromwell</hi> with his Curafficres and the reſt of my Lord <hi>Mancheſters</hi> Horſe, who were placed in the right wing, fell with ſuch force and fury upon the Lord <hi>Gorings</hi> Briga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des on the Right, that they preſently broke them in pieces, and following their ſucceſſe before the Prince returned, obtained a compleat Victory, killing no leſſe then 5000 Men, gaining their Camp, Bag and Baggage, and as the price of all, the City of <hi>York:</hi> Hence he acquired that terrible name of <hi>Ironſides,</hi> his Troops being reported unvulnerable and unconquerable; by this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he feat, lifted up himſelf to thoſe great Titles and Places he went through afterwards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:44909:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>A continuance of his ſucceſſes againſt his Soveraign and his Forces, his Treacherous and Diſloyal dealing with his Majeſty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe next Field we finde him in, was that of the ſecond <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry, October</hi> the 27 1644. where with the ſame Felicity and Valour, he had the better on that part of the Field, where he Fought, and contributed mainly to that piece of a Victory the Parliament Forces had there; when to cloud and damp this ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Martialliſt, he was Articled againſt by his Superiour Officers for ſome miſcarriages and practiſes in the Army, to the hindrance of the ſervice, which was indeed his ambitious inſinuation into the affection of the Souldiery: but this was never proſecuted, his Friends the Grandees of the Independent party, interpoſing and juſtifying him for a godly, expert and Valiant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander.</p>
               <p>This Independent Faction was now grown too crafty, and had ſupplanted their Brother of Presbytery, by new modelling the Army, turning out moſt of <hi>Eſſexes</hi> Officers, and diſmiſſing all Members of Parliament from their ſeveral Commands therein; among which number <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſhould have been included, but his <hi>partiſans</hi> wrought ſo, that he was continued for Forty dayes, and thoſe expired longer and longer even till the War ended. By this ſaid model Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> was made Lord General, and <hi>Cromwell</hi> after ſome time Lieutenant General, being the only man lookt upon able to carry on the independent Intereſt. The firſt action he engaged in in this quality, was his routing of the Queens Regiment and ſome other Troops (come from <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> to fetch the King from <hi>Oxford,</hi> then deſigned to be beſieged in the beginning of the year 1645.) at <hi>Iſlip bridge:</hi> then his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate ſummoning and taking <hi>Blechingdon</hi> Houſe, <hi>April 24th.</hi> whereafter as he was deſigning a ſtratagem upon <hi>Faringdon</hi> Houſe, he was ſet upon by as vigilant a Commander as himſelf, the Lord <hi>Goring,</hi> and received a ſmart bruſh, and the onely one throughout the War; which now haſtning to an end at the Fatal <hi>Nasby,</hi> he was called from out the <hi>Iſle of Ely</hi> (whither he had been lately ſent to ſecure it, it being thought the King would have turn'd his now ſucceſſeful Armes thitherward) to aſſiſt the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44909:6"/>who by his Letters to the Parliament had deſired it. That Unfortunate day the 14th. of <hi>June,</hi> 1646. owes it's diſmalneſs to the Fortune of this Rebel whoſe Troops alone could glory in that Atchievment; for the left wing of that Army, where <hi>Ireton</hi> his Sonne in Law Commanded, was abſolutely routed and the main body ſolely diſtreſſed; ſo that <hi>Cromwell</hi> alone aſſured that Victory.</p>
               <p>So ended the firſt War with the Praiſes and Triumphs of this Man of War, Adored and Worſhipped by the Raſcal Rabble of Independency, who ſtuck not to Blaſpheme God and his Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures attributing all thoſe <hi>Hoſanna's</hi> and Pſalmes, and Songs of Deliverance and Victory to this their Champion; in effect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a meer Idol of Him, which Phanatick Religious Veneration, he miſt not to improve, though for the preſent he covered his ambition with modeſty and humility, aſcribing all things in a Canting way of expreſſion, to the goodneſſe and omnipotence of God, which he frequently and impiouſly abuſed, intituling it to all his wicked and Villanous deſignes and actions.</p>
               <p>The War thus ended, and the KING having eſcaped their Swords, and ſo the main rub yet lay in the way to his projected ſoveraignty; he reſolved by Treachery to ruine him; to that purpoſe, that he might render the King indiſpoſed to the Terms and Propoſitions of the Parliament, which were hard and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable enough beſides; he pretended to the King that the Army ſhould take his part and declare for him: as on the other ſide in the Parliament Houſe, &amp; privately in the Army (telling them that the Kings deſigne of peace and Agreement was onely to get them Disbanded, and then Hang them for their Rebellion) he exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated them againſt the King, adding that God had hardned his heart againſt any compoſure, and had rejected him: and when all this would not doe, but that the people every day more and more were undeceived, and he conceived a fear they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue the <hi>King</hi> from <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> &amp; bring him to <hi>London</hi> which the King and all good men deſired; he contrived another wicked Device to the Kings Final Overthrow, by ſcaring him with the Adjucators (ſuch were two ſelected out of each Company and Troop) conſpiracy to aſſaſſinate him, and ſo making him fl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> a diſtant and ſure priſon, from whence he never came but to his Death. The King a while before was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44909:6"/>of theſe Treacherous arts of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> ſeeing nothing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as to ſubſtance of what ever he promiſed, and therefore did roundly Tax him with his Faithleſſeneſſe; who at the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot told the King that He did miſconſtrue his words, or elſe he remembred no ſuch matter, and that if it were ſo, yet it were no time to perform them, till the Diſcipline of the Army was reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and choſe Adjutators in a capacity to be queſtioned, who were now moſt outragiouſly and uncontroulably violent againſt his perſon and Government, with many more ſuch Flams and Delayes, and Traiterous Fallacies.</p>
               <p>The King being in priſon at <hi>Carisbroke Caſtle</hi> in the ſaid Iſle, by the jugling of <hi>Cromwell</hi> with <hi>Hammond</hi> the Governour (Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to one of the Kings moſt affected Chaplains) an ungrateful Fellow, who owed himſelf to the Kings bounty; ſeveral freſh at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts were made for his reſtitution: that which particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned this <hi>Oliver,</hi> was the Welſh inſurrection at <hi>Pembroke,</hi> which Town in <hi>July,</hi> after a brave defence was rendred to him. and the <hi>Scots</hi> invaſion under Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> whoſe Army, to which were joyned ſome Three Thouſand Engliſh under Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale,</hi> he totally defeated at <hi>Preſton</hi> in <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> on the 17th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> (and not long after the General <hi>Fairfax</hi> took in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> which had ſtood out Three months (in expectation of relief from this Army) upon the ſame account) and purſued his Victory as farre as <hi>Scotland,</hi> marching to <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and there making ſure of a party, dealing with Bribes and other forceable perſwaſions, and making them diſarm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to give him no diſturbance or interruption in the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing his moſt execrable Regicide, for which he was now ready; the expected advantages and opportunities being now in his Hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Cromwell <hi>turnes out the Parliament, Murders the</hi> King, <hi>ſets up a</hi> Commonwealth, <hi>who invading</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>make him their</hi> General.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CRomwell</hi> poſting to <hi>London,</hi> and he and his Sonne <hi>Ireton</hi> put the Council of Officers to demand <hi>Justice</hi> upon the King as the Capital Offendor, and Authour of all the Troubles and Bloodſhed: which he ſo eagerly proſecuted, that though the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44909:7"/>had nearly concluded with the King in the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> after a full Treaty, he by Col. <hi>Pride,</hi> one that would venture upon any thing he was commanded by him, Secludes twice the Major part of the Members, and then packs up a Juncto of Army Blades, of ſome Fifty, who conſtitute a <hi>High Court of Justice,</hi> by which the Martyr King was Traiterouſly and Barbarouſly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and Beheaded, <hi>January</hi> the 30. By the ſame <hi>Juncto</hi> and <hi>Rump</hi> of a Parliament, the King ſhip and Government by a ſingle Perſon was Voted uſeleſſe and dangerous, to which <hi>Cromwell</hi> freely aſſented, as purpoſing to time his Ambition, now the great Obſtacle was removed.</p>
               <p>But though the King and his Intereſt were defunct in <hi>England,</hi> yet they were not in <hi>Ireland</hi> or <hi>Scotland;</hi> whereupon, <hi>Cromwell</hi> is made General for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Expedition, and though he was the only diſwader of the Souldiery from that ſervice, during the quarrel betwixt the Independants and the Presbyterians, and while he had accompliſhed his miſchievous Ends upon the King; yet now he is ſeverely bent to tranſport ſuch as the Lot ſhould appoint: which the Levelling party, the Adjutators, Whelps of his own Litter, refuſing and mutining, them likewiſe under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Treaty, and giving and receiving ſatisfaction (their uſual expreſſions) he betraies and ſurprizes at <hi>Burford</hi> (not daring to venture a Fight with them for fear of a Total defection of his own party) and had the Ring-leaders ſhot to Death.</p>
               <p>Having ſurmounted this difficulty, he wafts his Army over into <hi>Iréland,</hi> and preſently ſtorms <hi>Tredagh,</hi> and underſtanding it was the Flower of the Kings Army, ſet there to give him a repulſe, having twice bin beaten off, he led his men himſelf the third time and entred, and put all to the Sword, (having amuſed the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants who maintained the breach; but having then loſt their Colonel, were in ſome confuſion through offer of Quarter,) and by that device got admittance) with alike baſeneſſe, treachery and cruelty.</p>
               <p>After that followed the rendition of moſt of that Kingdome, the Lord Lievtenant thereof, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> being in no Condition to reſiſt him: whereupon the <hi>Scotch</hi> War then newly beginning, <hi>Cromwell</hi> was ſent for over, and the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Miniſters, ſet on no doubt by ſome of his Agents, having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigled <hi>Fairfax</hi> with the unlawfulneſſe of his engaging againſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44909:7"/>their Gude brethren; he laid down his Commiſſion, which was readily conferred on, and taken up by <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of</hi> Cromwells <hi>March into</hi> Scotland, <hi>his Victories at</hi> Dunbar <hi>and</hi> Worceſter, <hi>and the reduction of that Kingdome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GLadly did <hi>Oliver</hi> undertake this War, for now he was ſure to make the Army his own, by placing and diſplacing of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; long it was, and many delayes were uſed by the <hi>Scots,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would be brought to Fight, intending to ſtarve the Engliſh Army, which was neer done to their Hands, and <hi>Oliver</hi> ſneaking away Home, when the precipitate <hi>blew cap</hi> greedy of Spoyle and Victory, would needs fall upon them at <hi>Dunbar, Sept.</hi> 3d. 1650. and were there by the proweſſe and deſperate Valour of their Enemies totally overcome. <hi>Cromwell</hi> therefore now Marches back again to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and buyes that impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Caſtle of the Traytor <hi>Dundaſſe,</hi> and advances againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, who lay Encamped by <hi>Sterling;</hi> but he not ſtirring out of his fortified Camp, and there being no other or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſage into <hi>Scotland,</hi> but over the Frith an Arm of the Sea: <hi>Cromwell</hi> wafts over moſt part of his Army, and defeats a <hi>Scotch</hi> party, while the King gives <hi>Cromwell</hi> the Go-by, being two dayes march before him, and after a tedious march came to <hi>Worceſter, Auguſt</hi> the 22d. whither not long after came <hi>Cromwell</hi> in great doubt and perplexity by the way, (having left General <hi>Monk</hi> to carry on the War in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who ſhortly after reduced the whole Kingdome) and beſet the Town, being recruited and made up with his old Army, to above Forty Thouſand Men; what ſhall I ſay of that Unfortunate day? the King was Worſted, and moſt miraculouſly eſcaped, and ſo <hi>Cromwell</hi> might have leave to play.</p>
               <p>But no ſuch matter, the time was come he had long expected, to act his own Game and appear in it for himſelf, for by the year 1653. <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> being wholy ſubdued, &amp; in the hands of his moſt truſty Privado's and Confidents, his New Son-in-Law <hi>Fleetwood</hi> (for <hi>Ireton</hi> was dead of the Plague at <hi>Limbrick</hi>) being Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and General <hi>Monck</hi> Governour of <hi>Scotland;</hi> he propoſeth to the Parliament, the deſires of the Army for their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44909:8"/>Diſſolution, to make way for ſucceſſion of a new Repreſentative, which they endeavouring to delay, and to impoſe upon him with the neceſſities of their ſitting a little while longer; his Ambition could brook no longer retardments, but ſent Major General <hi>Harriſon</hi> on the 20th. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1653. to out their Rump-ſhips which he accordingly did, to the general rejoycing of the people, who conſidered nor cared who ſhould come next, ſo they were rsid of theſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>How</hi> Cromwell <hi>ordered the Government afterward, and how he made himſelf Lord Protector of</hi> England.</head>
               <p>AFter the RUMP was thus diſſolved, <hi>Oliver</hi> by the adviſe (forſooth) of his General Councel of Officers, erected a Councel of State, of ſuch as were true to his Intereſt and the Army, and were well Fledg'd with the ſpoyles of the Kingdome, but perceiving that was but a ſlender Authority, to derive the Government to himſelf, which was the firſt and laſt thing inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; he called a pickt Conventicle of the like batch as himſelf and his Followers, all of the Godly party, whom he ſtiled a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; the name whereof was enough to Authorize and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Reſignation of the Authority they had from, to, him; &amp; their odious actions moreover would make a ſingle perſon (him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) more acceptable; For theſe wild Fellows were upon Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the Miniſtry, and opening the Floodgate to Hereſie and Atheiſme; when <hi>Cromwell</hi> diſſolved them, and with them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded his old Friend and their darling, Major General <hi>Harriſon,</hi> who was tampering with the Army to unhorſe <hi>Oliver;</hi> but he ſmelt him out and Caſhiered him, as he did his Truſty Friend <hi>Lambert</hi> ſoon after, as finding they were both greater in the Army then his Safety and Intereſt would ſuffer: ſo impoſſible it is for brethren in iniquity long to continue in Love and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. <hi>Oliver</hi> would endure no Competitor, but reſolved to be Single and Supreme:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:44909:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>How</hi> Oliver <hi>was ſworn Protector, and how be managed the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, briefly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat little or fooliſh Parliament being divided among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, one part thereof reſigned their power unto <hi>Oliver,</hi> who ſtraight with cauſed the Commiſſioner of the Seale Mr. <hi>Liſle,</hi> to Adminiſter him an Oath on the 16th. of <hi>December,</hi> 1653. before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall,</hi> to obſerve a Module of Government in Forty Two Articles; which inſtrument of his, as was ſaid, was found in my Lady <hi>Lamberts</hi> placket, and thereupon he was proclaimed Lord Protector; in <hi>February</hi> he was feaſted ſumptuouſly in the City, and Knighted the Lord Mayor, as he did many other afterwards, upon whom he had better have piſſed: he made alſo one Lord, but he never owned it. Now though he was proclaimed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, yet he knew the people took him for no ſuch thing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he called a <hi>parliament</hi> according to Form, thinking to have been declared ſo by them, but they would not own him or his Authority. Seeing therefore he could neither get Reputation nor Money at home, he reſolved to have it from the King of <hi>Spains Weſt-Indies,</hi> but at <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> his Forces under General <hi>Venables</hi> were ſtrangely defeated, and forced to plant themſelves in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and fight for Bread inſtead of Gold. He likewiſe ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeveral plots, (the Fox was the finder) againſt Cavaliers, ſuch as Colonel <hi>Gerrard,</hi> and afterwards Colonel <hi>Penruddock</hi> (main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining intelligence at the price of 1500. <hi>per annum,</hi> with one <hi>Manning</hi> a Clerk to the Kings Secretary, who then reſided at <hi>Colen,</hi> who diſcovered moſt of the Kings Councel, till he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered himſelf and executed) on purpoſe to terrifie people, and thoſe eſpecially from riſing againſt him.</p>
               <p>Now when <hi>Oliver</hi> ſaw he could not attaine his will by whole Parliaments, he reſolved on his old expedient, to garble a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Call it, and then Cull it, which he did, and ſecluded thoſe Members that would not before they entred, recognize and own his Highneſſe; by which means two parts of three were excluded, and he by the remainder complemented with the ſtile of King, but for fear of <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Harriſon,</hi> and indeed the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44909:9"/>eſpecially the Army, he durſt not accept of it, but was content to take the Title of Protector from their Hands, and was accordingly on the 16th. of <hi>June,</hi> 1657. Solemnly inſtalled by the Speaker, Sir <hi>Thomas Widdrington</hi> again in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and the Parliament adjourned, who had likewiſe paſſed an Act for erecting of a thing called another Houſe, conſiſting of ſuch Lords as <hi>Pride, Hewſon</hi> and <hi>Barkſtead;</hi> but upon the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a full Houſe, after the Adjournment, all this new ſtructure was queſtioned even to <hi>Oliver</hi> himſelf, who thereupon in a paſſion, and tranſported beyond his vizarded ſanctity, with an Oath by the Living God, diſſolved them.</p>
               <p>In the year 1658. he aſſiſted the <hi>French</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and helped them to take <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> which for his pains he had delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him, and no doubt it was the beſt ſervice he ever did to his Countrey. But during this unenvied triumph, having drencht his polluted hands in more innocent and Loyal Blood; namely, that of Dr. <hi>Hewet,</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby,</hi> God put a Hook into the mouth of this <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and having ſnatcht away his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Daughter <hi>Claypoole</hi> juſt before; on the 3d. of <hi>September</hi> 1658. his great ſucceſsful day, he was hurried in a Tempeſt out of the world, which he had ſo long troubled, and on the 16th. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> following, was moſt magnificently buried, to the onely ſorrow of thoſe who furniſhed the Mourning, and Pageantry thereof, leauing his Wife <hi>Elizabeth</hi> alias <hi>Jone,</hi> with two Sonnes, <hi>Richard,</hi> who ſucceeded, till he tamely and Cowardly reſigned &amp; is now fled for his Fathers Debts, &amp; <hi>Henry,</hi> and a Daughter y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleped <hi>Francis Rich.</hi> A Perſon as it was well charactered of him, fit to be a Prince of <hi>Tartars</hi> or Cannibals.</p>
               <p>Before the King returned into <hi>England,</hi> Colonel <hi>Henry Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> Sonne of Sir <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> obtained licenſe of the King to change that hateful name into <hi>Williams,</hi> which was the name of this Family, before they married with a Daughter and Heir of of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> which was upon Condition they ſhould take her Name as well as Eſtate.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
